What is this?
It is a Fordson DEXTA from 1964.
-What do you use it for?
I have to compete with it.
I run a tractor race, tractor-speedway and tractor-cross we run in Målilla.
-Tractor-cross?
Yes we drive on a cross track.
-Is it even possible?
It is possible but it is bounce.
-It's no suspension on a tractor?
No suspension at all just the tires that swing.
We are completely stuck in the chair without cushioning.
It works but it feels in the body when you have run some race.
-Was there several different branches?
For the most part we run TRAKOR-RACE it is slalom and then we drive between set bales.
We run 5-6 competitions a year starting in June until October.
-Is there any competition in the future (going forward)?
Yes it is Hylletofta on September 14th.
That's what we are charging for right now.
May hope the stuff holds.
There has been some problems this year because it tempts pretty hard on the stuff.
It is a completely standard Volvo 850 engine with original crankshes, etc., it is not opened.
A little for a single tractor in really but you learn to drive it.
How do you get the idea to put a Volvo car engine in a tractor?
Hmmm ... you have too much free time.
-Who have come up with the idea to trim a tractor?
Yes that is a good question ... I think it started with that ...
Should you buy it?
Yes I can do that ... so I brought it home.
It stood in the workshop for a few years before I built it together.
It was not supposed that I would compete with it but just just a fun thing to build a tractor with a car engine.
Then was it a friend outside Sävsjö who asked if I would be on a tractor race?
What does that mean?
I said.
Well you drive slalom between bales, etc.
Okay, I can join.
I went to the scrap and picked up a cabin arch that I mounted and competed.
The first race I was 2a.
It gave added flavor ...
... it just continued and then more people were interested in the municipality.
Then we started a team.
Team Hylletofta.
Fordson is an English tractor.
It came in the early 1960s, perhaps even in the late 50's around 1958-59.
I don't have 100% control over history.
This particular model has learned a lot because I have screwed a lot with it.
This engine has a little more horses than DEXTRA has.
Super DEXTRA was a snap better than Dextra you could say.
-What do you use this tractor for?
I have it as a truck.
I built a pair of pallet forks together so I can lift all my gearboxes and rear axles.
So it doesn't tempt my back too much.
It is a farm's wear and toss tractor you can say.
The idea is that it will get a refresh.
Now I have bought so many tractors because they break.
It is difficult to get hold of parts.
When I drove the rear axle last year, I called five different tractor scraps and there were no stuff.
Then I got a little panic because it took me 2 months to get hold of spare parts.
After work, every weekend.
All the free time you had over you on the tractor.
Many friends pushed that now it is soon Målilla you have to finish with the tractor.
A week before Målilla we made the first start on the tractor.
Then it was 03:44 when it started in the garage.
Then my friend Jesper Fager was here and connected the computer because it did not light.
Then we had problems with trigger and get all the settings correctly.
But Jesper said I don't go home first it starts and we were very tired everyone.
People who were here watching went home because it was in the middle of the night, it is really crazy.
I am passionate about what you just want it to work.
When we got the tractor running we were pretty tired so we continued on Monday.
Then when I was out and tested and realized that it leaks oil from crankshaft seal.
Then you became quite less and said that you ignore this and can not hold on anymore.
I'll be going to Målilla next year ...
... but then the friends came and said we help you remove the engine.
Call and ask if you can be free tomorrow.
At 22:45 we rolled the tractor into the workshop and at 00:20 the engine lay on the floor.
With the help of Natanael Ceder from Maxxtuning in Vrigstad.
Then it went away to Målilla.
I was thinking about one thing.
The front car when I compare to the original tractor.
This is what the original front car looks like.
This one is a little reinforced.
Because I have built a frame on the tractor.
So I have had to move out the stabilization stages.
They sit in the outer holes watch the other tractor so they sit in the interior.
I have widened the shoulder.
You can see that there are holes here.
I have moved out the shoulder and sanded out of the holes.
So I can angle the spindle joints so I get another camber.
They have had problems that they have gone off therefore I have strengthened on the inside.
So you have welded on a plate on the back.
Why do you have weights on it on the side?
Because the tractor is so short.
It works differently from competition to competition.
This one is very smooth and I easily turn it around.
The disadvantage of a short wheelbase is that it wants to bounce and goes very much on the rear wheels.
And then you want to get the weight down.
I have made an abdominal plate in 15 mm sheet so it helps.
If it is not enough and wants to get the bite into the rear axle.
Then I have put weights here that weigh 40 kg each.
So I have 120 kg on each side.
Then I feel that the tractor becomes steady.
Is the protection on the Speedway protection page?
Yes and for tractor cross.
It is when we drive several at the same time.
When we drive slalom we drive on each path.
When it can be close contact, we have these pipes.
That pipe should be along so nothing can come in between.
-How phase you got this puzzle together ...
It was to think about first and foremost to think how long you want the tractor.
The engine is based on quite far.
I wanted hydraulic coupling so it should be easy to connect.
This holds the gearbox underneath and I have made an adapter.
To get the car engine together with the tractor.
Many times an adapter plate is built on the tractor or against the tractor's explosive cover.
In this case, I chose to cut away so much on the blast cover.
I took the angle grinder and cut it off.
Then I talked to a friend here in Sävsjö who works at a company with a mill.
He milled off the cover so I had to measure all dimensions.
I have taken from the dimensions from a Volvo 850 input shaft.
But has the tractor's input shaft.
I drive with a flywheel from rear axle parts and a Sachs 765 pressure plate.
There is no longer the same clutch pedal.
I have taken it from a Volvo tractor.
It becomes like you drive a car.
For original, you switch and brake with the heel.
When driving you can decouple with the whole foot but with the heel.
Then it will be tough if you have a hard pressure plate.
So we have the cab.
There we have come to the conclusion that we have to cross the cage.
It is if you overturn so it holds together better.
I have chosen to put pipes here.
So it holds together better in the corner.
Have also chosen to tick the rear according to the rules.
I have made double crosses at the back to make it the belt.
The cabin is really just bolted at the screen an iron that goes down into the trumpet.
-The trumpet?
That is called the rear axle.
Radial tires are much softer.
I have chosen tires that fit the rim that they become straight.
If I swing on the tractor you can see that it is soft tires.
The tractor is not so bumpy anymore.
I had some problems when I was driving speedway and it went like a duck kid.
It is probably because it is short.
If it starts to bounce, it continues.
The only thing you can do about it is to stay but you don't ...
... first in goal wins.
Then you can't stop.
Why had you dubbed tires before?
It is so when you ball ideas with others who compete.
Rickard and some others also had ice tires ...
Yes, ice tires are probably good so you drive on that idea.
The first competition in Målilla I made a giants at the start.
When the tractor struck, the rim was flat because the tires are too hard.
So it broke the rims for me so I went home and balled ideas with others.
I cut out a couple of edges that I weld stuck on the inside of the rim.
The rims I have in there are reinforced.
Now I have tried to run original tractor tires and then it can withstand more bumps.
And it gets a little right.
It controls well and I never change tires now.
Before, I was changing all the time but it is hard.
-What is this?
Why do you have one?
It is the strength floor that sits there.
It is orbitrol control.
-Hydraulic control?
Do you have to have it?
It is much easier to swing.
If you have completely mechanically as original and you use the steering wheel ball and the nip to you have the kid wrist left ...
Hahaha!!
Many people get hurt when it shrugs.
Many people have done badly.
-You learn the hard way.
It had become very much steering when driving slalom.
Then they had to be stepped back and forth all the time.
Therefore, I have chosen to build power steering.
Then this is a very special sport ... -Yo thank you!
You have to be a little stupid in your head to keep up with this.
Many have agriculture.
I grew up in Sävsjö but have also been a lot in Hylletofta because my mother grew up there.
I was very much with Grandma and Grandpa when I was little.
It is well there from I have received it because I work with tractors now.
It is well from where I have been given the interest.
The engine is fully visible here.
I we can lift off the hood you will see.
Here I have my little screwdriver that I always have with me.
This must be easier than screwing a car?
It is open so you can access everything smoothly.
The engine I found on Facebook.
It was a loose engine from a Volvo 850 with gearbox and front car.
I have had help building a manifold.
-It looks like a snake.
Yep, it's designed by Jesper Fager.
There are straight pipes on this.
Yep there are straight pipes.
It's screampipe out of the Wastegaten.
I have pipes here that go from the cab to the front axle.
It is a reinforcement because I cracked the other tractor so you want it as strongly as possible.
What I have been thinking about updating for next season is the brakes.
It is drum brakes original and that is what we drive with.
Drum brakes stop working fairly quickly.
You disassemble and change the evidence ...
... run 2-3 competitions so they hardly take again.
Brakes are quite nice to have.
The idea is to build disc brakes.
This has been thought about how it should go.
This has been changed to disc brakes so there are ideas to build for next season.
It is probably the next step to go.
-Do you have a 4-point belt?
Yeah.
I have one that is quite wide.
Otherwise, it cuts in because it bounces so much.
The chair is silently mounted so the only suspension available is the wheels that swing.
When I have the wheel straight and full steering wheel is 2 laps but I never think about that.
You see that Christmas is straight ahead.
Because it's orbitrol control ...